here we go
so as usual we'll try to
relax your face relax your mouth
relax your eyelids
sit up straight
one way to sit up straight is to push
down
which forces your chest and head
up
it's always a good idea to tighten your
lower abdomen and
the way you do that is on your exhales
you can use your exhales as a
excuse to tighten your lower abdomen
and that tightens your that
strengthens your back muscles and you
can
sit up straight you can meditate longer
so let's take 10 deep breaths and
the exhales are very very long
uh much longer than usual
so at the end of the exhale your tummy
tightens
which strengthens your back and you can
sit for
longer periods of time
hands are any comfortable way
the goal with the hands is to keep them
out of the picture keep them out of the
way
just park them
i don't mind the sun it's good
now let's go through our five pictures
okay
for me i'm gonna use my old high school
and i'm gonna start on the tennis courts
and
think of a young
young man who's happy because he just
got a position on the tennis team
and what that represents is the first
benefit
of bodhichitta which is you you join the
team
of mahayana people again it's not a
mahayana
buddhist school it's a group of
extraordinary beings who have
had the experience of leaping from
planet to planet
and meeting people
every living being on each planet tens
of billions of
beings on each planet it's a very very
a special team a
very select group of people called
bodhisattvas
and if i could
burn this bodhichitta meditation into my
mind
i could join that team
how would that feel
hey
next go to a place
that you remember that will remind
you of a graduation
for me i i walk from the tennis courts
of my old high school
over to the football stadium
and that's where we had our graduation
what's the graduation picture mean
it means that the second benefit of
buddy china they will give you a title
you will have a new title they will call
you
bodhisattva girl saying bodhisattva alex
bodhisattva colleen and
you know it's like a phd title
or a doctor title
now the beings
in the universe who are
extraordinary they will always talk
about you as
as oh that bodhisattva
jigna and that bodhisattva tim
you will change your identity
firstly i like to spend about 10 breaths
10 slow breaths
on each part of the
path that i'd like to burn into my mind
the next idea we learned
was that you get a second title
which is gyaose daughter or
son of the buddha and
for me i'm thinking of a picture where
my
after my graduation my my mom and my dad
came and hugged me
and so a picture
of a father or mother buddha
coming to give me a hug
and welcome me into their family now i'm
their son or their daughter
and of course the buddhas love everybody
but once you
have jumped between planets and
met all the living beings and made this
commitment to help them
directly to them made the commitment
directly to them
each each one individually
then you sort of join a new family
and you are welcomed into that new
family
it's a very tight-knit
and the buddhas have a special feeling
for you
then in my high school picture i i go
from the
football field where my mom and dad
hugged me
after graduation over to a part of the
high school where
there were kids learning to be farmers
and they had donkeys
and that donkey reminds me
that we don't have to be geniuses
or moral geniuses to become a
bodhisattva
we don't have to be the smartest person
we don't have to be the best person
we can be ourselves we have lots of
problems
we have lots of weaknesses
we have addictions that we have
not been able to stop and we have
all kinds of bad habits we treat other
people
sometimes not very nice
but still we can become a bodhisattva
it's it's independent of those things we
can
have that experience we can have that
dream maybe the worse we are the better
we can dream
so even the text said even a donkey or
a fish or a bird
someone without great intellectual
qualities
someone who's a normal
person who fails from day to day week to
week
even in our practice but still that path
is available
to us we can become a bodhisattva
then the last picture for me at my high
school is i go to the
gymnasium and they build an extra
top on side of on outside the gymnasium
and i imagine a skyscraper
people sitting on a piece of a
skyscraper
and that reminds me of this
event in in my life where
it seemed like a whole building was
moving
shaking actually jumping from side to
side
and
that reminds me of what happens when any
person
jumps from planet to planet and reaches
lordy chitta becomes a bodhisattva
then because the karma of the whole
universe is linked together
the karma that created the physical
galaxy
those karmas are all linked together i'm
i'm
also responsible for mars i'm
responsible for
the sun i'm responsible for
buddha paradises that i heard about
and if my relationship with every living
being
changes suddenly then
that jolts the
karma that created the galaxy
and the galaxy jumps
and trembles from the weight of this new
kind of love that i found
the galaxy is the creation of my mind
my karma and
it serves all living beings if i decide
to serve those same beings
then the galaxy has to
jump when i do
and people
on some level all all people
and especially all buddhas are aware
that one of the one of us in the
galaxy just became a body sample
so imagine the day that you become a
bodhisattva
and the galaxy trembles
and let's dedicate the good karma
that everyone we know could become a
body supper
and then slowly open your eyes
take a stretch